Do you know that till September 2021, LIC has an
unclaimed amount of ₹21000 crore. No one came to claim it. Last year also, they had
an unclaimed amount of around ₹880 crore. I am talking about just one company. There
are 24-25 such life insurance companies in India where crores and billions of rupees are lying.
Because no one from the family reached there to claim it. You have purchased the policy
but the family members do not know that you have taken the policy and they
did not go to claim it because what happens most of the time when you purchase the policy,
most of the time in India, the husband purchases the policy and he
is either working in the office or working in a company. Suppose an advisor
came to meet him in the office to understand the policy. They purchased the policy and
forgot to inform their family members and when the claim came in the future, the family members did not know that
you had taken the policy of that company. So the first thing you have to do is that whenever
you purchase a policy of any insurance company, definitely inform your family members
because if they do not know then the claim will be for those for whom you had purchased this policy
. Your main objective is also to protect your family. So
you had taken the policy to protect them. But you did not inform them
that I have taken such a policy. So in the future, whenever
you purchase a policy of any company, definitely inform your family members. Secondly, many times people's claims
get rejected because they do not check the policy bond. Because there
many times the information gets mismatched. Let us assume that the customer
is very genuine and he has to purchase a policy term plan and he is only 10th pass. Now when he
went to purchase the policy, he told the advisor that he is 10th pass but the advisor said
sorry to say but it can happen and it happens many times. He
showed you as 12th pass or graduate and sent you the policy. Suppose your income is 4 lakhs but
to buy the policy, it is necessary to have an income of 5 lakhs. So you told 4 lakhs but
5 lakhs was written in the proposal form and your policy was issued and you did
not even open the proposal form to see what is written in the policy. So whenever you get
the policy bond, open the policy bond and see. Your mobile number is required, email ID
is required, address is required, the nominee's name is correct. There is no spelling error. In
the plan that was told to me, this maturity was going to come. This was the name of the plan. This
was the benefit illustration. Has the same benefit illustration come in your policy bond?
What was told was something else. Any other policy bond or any other type of premium has not
come. Are you getting the benefits and features that were explained to
you or not? And if any claim comes in the future,
how to process it? How
can you go online and visit the customer portal? How will the entire process of claim be? If you
want to update the nominee, address, PAN card, how
can you do it? All this information is mentioned in the details of the policy bond in today's era
. So today I am going to explain to you the policy bond of a term plus unique plan of Tata AIA Life Insurance
. Whether you purchase a policy term plan in the future
or purchase a savings plan or purchase a pension plan. The policy bond
comes in this manner and the common information is in this manner. So watch this video completely.
Where you will understand the policy bond, what details are mentioned in the policy bond
. Where are the details mentioned. How can you email or SMS for the service
. How can you message customer care? Which
toll free number will be for you? So I am explaining
all these details to you in this video . If you like the video, then
definitely like, share and subscribe my YouTube channel Anil Raj Trough FS. In future also
I will explain similar policy bonds to different companies. Those
will also be helpful for you. My name is Anil Rajpurohit. I am an MBA Finance.
I have been working in the corporate sector for 15 years and there
are more than 300 insurance related videos on my YouTube channel which will help you in your financial planning. So
do not forget to subscribe to the channel. Now let us understand
how you can read the bond when you get the policy bond. Like this
is the Term Plus Uli Plan of Tata AIA. I am giving you its PDF. You can see all similar
savings policies or pure term policies or pension plans.
It will come. First of all, your name, your address, your mobile number etc.
will be mentioned here. Do check the spelling once. The name of the plan that
you are purchasing will be mentioned here.
Here I have edited the details of the real customer a little because I
do not want their details to be made public. So, some details here
will appear incomplete because I have edited them. Now you will see here
that the customer's name will be visible here. His address will be visible here. The mobile
number will be visible here. The name of the plan will be visible here.
In the table of content, you will see all the things that you will see in this policy bond.
The policy schedule number will be visible. On which page? On the eighth page. The features
of this plan. You will see them on the 12th page. You can see the service options on the 19th page
. You will get information about the proposal form on the 30th page.
You will get information about the benefit illustration on the 37th page. It is the unit statement. How much
money did you invest and what is the NAV. You
will get information about which fund the investment is in on page number 58. And you
will get the receipt of the first premium you paid for your policy on page number 60. That means
a policy bond of about 60 pages will come to your home. You
will get the physical bond and the electronic bond on email. What will you see in the policy schedule?
What is the name of the policy holder? What is the name of the life insured? What is the address? What is the mobile number?
Client ID, what is their age, date of birth etc.? Gender and which plan
are they purchasing? How much basic insurance cover is taken in it. When did this policy start
? How much premium are you paying? How many years is the policy term visible here
. For how many years do you have to pay the premium? You
will see all this information here, how much premium have you paid in total
. Here the most important thing you will see is reduction in yield because ULIP is plus
ULIP plus term policy, so there are some charges here, so
how much percentage of your yield or returns
can be affected by these charges in which year. Suppose in the 40th year, your impact
is only around 3%. But in the beginning it will be more because in the beginning the charges are more. So this is
also an important thing you will see here. Plus who have you kept as nominee? Nominee
details will appear. You can keep three nominees also. How much percentage of
benefit will the nominee get? You can also mention that here. If you
are taking a traditional policy and the life insurance there is minor, then
you have to keep an appointee there. So you will see the appointment details here.
Talking about the policy schedules, here you
also get accidental death benefit and disability rider. Because it is a term plus uli policy, you will also
get information about them here, how much is your accidental cover, how much are your disabilities
being covered and for how many years will this cover be, in which year will it start,
what will be the last date of premium, what will be the maturity date for you in the policy, what
will be the different premiums of the riders, you
will get to see them here in the policy bond, along with this,
you will also get information about the features of this plan here, here
your money will get returns in market link, you will also get returns as per the market link,
you will get an opportunity to invest in different funds,
there will also be life insurance cover, you will also get the benefits of wellness, what will you get on maturity benefit, it
will be mentioned here, what will you get on death benefit, it will be mentioned here,
the charges that are being deducted from you in loyalty addition, from the 11th year onwards, you
are getting double the mortality charges, you are getting double the premium allocation charges. There are benefits of cover
continuity. You get a grace period of 15 days and 30 days.
The waiting period is zero. That means your insurance cover starts from the first day itself
. What will be the exclusions? What riders have you purchased?
You will also see the benefits of vitality. Today I am making this video
on 18 August 2025. At this time I think that the new plan which is running, Param Raksha Live Pro
Plus and its series, they have probably stopped
the benefits of vitality in it just now. Before that, these were the benefits of vitality. Where you
take care of your health, then you used to get some discount on renewal. But if you
took renewal discount in the beginning and do not take care of health. This measure of doing
If you had not taken care of the points, your premium could have increased. At present, I
think they have stopped the benefits of vitality. If you
have already taken an old policy of vitality, then how
can you take the benefit of vitality? In what way you can download an application here and
through that you can take the benefit of vitality.
Apart from this, the benefits of wellness have also been mentioned as to how you
can book consultation etc. Here you will find all these details
mentioned in the PDF of the entire policy. I come to the main things which
are very important for you. First of all, if you want information about your policy,
then go to this link and enter your policy number. Enter the date of birth
and there you will also be able to see your policy online. Where you enter your
date of birth and through that you will get an OTP. By entering the OTP, you
can also see the whole thing of your policy online. Where you
will find the complete dashboard. Even if you have purchased three or four policies of Tata, you
can see it there. Whether you want to download the premium payment receipt or the unit link of your
policy, how much is the fund value, statement etc., in which fund
the investment is being made, if you need all this information, then you
can see all these things by clicking here as I tell you. So here you will open that
PDF online link and you will be able to do it from there.
Here you have been given more information that to pay the premium, you
can go to the Tata AI website. You can click on this link.
Okay? You will directly reach the website.
You will directly reach the accounts if you click on the digital account which is DG account. Or if you
want to pay by different modes like you want to pay by credit card,
net banking or mobile wallet, then in this way also you
can pay the future premium of renewal . If you want to get ECS registered,
you can register ECS through this link. So in future,
money will be automatically deducted from your bank account or credit card. How can you get a digital policy?
You can get it through SMS, email. You
can also order it on WhatsApp. I have told you about the DG account.
You will also be able to access the documents of the digital policy through Digilocker and e-insurance account. The most important is
the claim process. If a claim comes, how will you be able to claim?
You will be able to do it with the registered document. Let me tell you the process.
What will you do first? The first option is that you can email
to clims@tata.com or you can WhatsApp
on the number 7045696. You can type the claim and WhatsApp it.
You can go to the Tata AI website. This link is written. You will click on this link
. You will reach the website directly and there you will get direct details
related to the claim . If you need information about the nearest branch, click on the link
. You will get information about the nearest branch. You can go there or you
can send a letter and all the details to Tata AI at this address.
This YouTube link is given to show how claim settlement works.
You can also watch a video on YouTube by clicking on this link to see how
you can make a claim. So the company has given you all the details in a very good way
that you can also email, WhatsApp, visit the website
, visit the branch, send us documents,
go to YouTube and understand how to process. If you have any query,
you can email customer care@ tata.com. I
am not talking about a claim query. It can be a normal query. Suppose you
have an error in your spelling or you want to change the nominee or you need information about anything else, you
can do it on this email ID. You can WhatsApp here.
You can call on the toll free number. Between 10:00 am to 7:00 pm
if you are outside India and are an NRI, you can call on this toll free number. You
can send an SMS. In this way,
I have already told you about the end or end nearest branch
by writing the policy number and registered email ID . Now suppose you have some personal details which you want to update. Like
for example, if there is some error in your name or some typing error in the email ID
, what will you do? You can go to your DG account and you can change your name there.
You can edit all the details like name, email ID, mobile number, NFT details, PAN, address, ECS details, etc.
If you want to make changes, you can do so. If
you have not received a physical policy, you have received only a digital one and you
want to get a physical one, you can email customer care@tata.com and you can
also get a physical copy of the policy. If you want to update the nominee and beneficiary details,
you can do so by going to My DG Account or
by visiting Tata's website or by visiting the nearest Tata branch. You have
to change the frequency of premium payment,
suppose if you are paying premium annually, you
want to do it every 6 months or monthly or if you are paying premium on a monthly basis, you
want to change it to annual mode, you can do it from My DG Account or you
can go to the nearest branch. So this My DG Account is a very important
thing which you can easily do from your mobile or laptop sitting at home.
Now you will see the customer sheet here. In the customer sheet,
you will find the policy number, name of the plan, how much
natural cover you have taken, how much accidental cover you have taken, all these things will be mentioned.
I will explain the important things in detail here. Suppose you have
accidental death benefit because ₹1 crore 44 lakhs is mentioned in this policy.
So if you die in an accident, you also get ₹14 lakhs. If there is a natural death, then
the insurance is also available. But there is a benefit in Tata that you get double the accidental cover
in some cases. So I will try to explain
to you in which cases you get that . For example,
life insured is riding as a passenger on commercially licensed public
transportation, i.e. public transportation in which, like train
, bus, government bus, if any accident happens in it, then
your accidental cover will be doubled to the nominee.
Or while life insured elevator cars, for example,
if some such cars are used there, if any
problem happens in it, if any accident happens there, then also double benefit will be given.
If there is any public gathering in a public building like theatre, cinema, public auditorium
, hotels, schools, hospitals, any accident happens there. Suppose a fire
breaks out and death happens, then accidental cover is available as double benefit. Or
if any incident happens in airlines etc., then you get double benefit.
You also get double disability cover. In which cases?
Same as these cases which we just saw in accidental death. Similarly,
if disabilities also occur. In many accidents, the person does not die.
He becomes disabled. He becomes crippled. Here we
are talking about total permanent disabilities. If not permanent, then you get double benefit there also. If you
become disabled while alive, then you get double benefit. Suppose there was an insurance cover of 1.44 lakhs,
then you have got 2.88 CR and the policy is continuing because you
are alive and you also get returns as per the market. So it will be like this.
What will you get on natural benefit? If nothing happens to you, then you
get the fund value. What is the meaning of accidental death? It has been explained here in detail
. We will also try to understand here what exclusions will be there
. You will see the information about disabilities in full detail in your policy here
. There will be no waiting period here.
We have already understood the process of claim. We
have already talked about policy servicing.
If you have any complaint, you
can also complain in grievance on this email id lplts@tata.com.
Free look period If you have taken the policy in physical mode, then it
will be 15 days and in digital mode you get a free look period of 30 days. If you
want to cancel the policy for any reason and get your money back, you can do so. But the most
important thing is your obligation. What are the most important things for you? When
you purchase the policy, do disclose all pre-existing diseases.
If you do not disclose, non-disclosure results in the claim not being
paid. Then your claim can also be rejected. That is why whenever you purchase the policy, if
you have any health condition, do mention it.
Do mention it in the proposal form. [Music]
Here you will see the proposal form. Where all your information will be there.
There will be all the information about the insurance cover. For how many years the premium has to be paid, for how many years
the policy will run, what premium will be charged, what riders are taken, you
will see all that information in the proposal form. In which fund your investment is going, what
percentage of your investment is going. All your details will be mentioned here.
I have hidden some details here. Your address etc. will all be mentioned. Now
I will tell you one more important thing. Let us assume that sometimes I
am just guessing. A lot of people are honest. But sometimes what happens
is that the customer's income is low and that policy, say a term policy, is not available,
then the agent may increase your income and write it down. This may help you get the policy
or for a businessman more income is required, for a salary it is less, so it is possible that he may
change your profile by increasing or decreasing it. Or suppose you are not even 10th pass.
But here a graduate can easily get a policy. So you have been shown as a graduate
. So whenever you purchase a policy, you
are given these details on page number 31. So go here and see if your education is written correctly. Suppose you
are 10th pass then it is written 10th pass. If your income is 7 lakhs then it
is also written? Are you self-employed? Is it written self-employed or salary
. So do check here. This can make a big difference in your policy
because I have seen many such cases where a person with less than 10th pass
has been given the policy. Whereas being a graduate
is mandatory in that plan. Suppose in this policy, even 10th pass can get it for example.
But there are many such plans which are available only to graduates. It is available to 12th pass
or to those with more than 5 lakh income. Now the customer's income is 4 lakh
but 5 lakh has been written in the proposal form. So you must check your policy board here
to see what is written there. You must also check your height and weight because
many times your height and weight are more. Your weight is more. But it is possible that
you have deliberately shown less weight so that you do not get extra premium or
the policy does not get cancelled or it is possible that your agent has deliberately
reduced your weight without telling you and you got the policy easily. Plus if you
eat tobacco gut mawa then you must mention it here because as I have just mentioned,
if you hide anything then your claim can also get rejected in the policy.
You must read all these questions once to see in which you have to write yes and in which you have to write no.
Like here the customer has mentioned yes at one place. Okay?
If you see here, he had informed the company about his health condition
. You must also inform. So here all the questions will be asked to you. You
must read these questions once in detail .
Family details If the life insured
is minor then family details are required here.
Do mention the existing insurance policy also. Like you already have a policy in LIC or Max Life Insurance
as mentioned by the customer here. Now let us assume that your income is 5 lakhs and
you are 40 years old then you get 20 times insurance. That means
you can take insurance cover of 1 crore. Let us assume that you already have an insurance
policy of 20 lakhs somewhere. But you did not show the existing insurance and you
have taken a policy of 1 crore here. So you got it because you
had zero insurance. But if you go according to human life value or the company's underwriting
then you were eligible for 1 crore. If you already had
an insurance cover of 20 lakhs then you will be able to take insurance cover of only 80 lakhs. So you
should also mention your existing insurance policy.
Apart from this, you are not able to see the sign here
because when you purchase the policy online and when you
provide the OTP, you get the policy from that also.
Do check this benefit illustration. Whenever you purchase the policy,
whatever you have been told, all that is written here. All your information,
in which funds your investment has gone, will be seen here.
All this premium you have to pay, all this will be seen here. What
will be the fund value? What will be the maturity? If it is a guaranteed policy, then the maturity
is written as guaranteed. If it is a bonus policy, then what are the bonuses? All those
tables are mentioned here, how much money is your premium allocation here.
How much will go to it. How much will go to motalities. How many charges, say 29,000, are deducted, then
you will get double of it back here. So all these things
are already mentioned here. So whatever benefit illustration your advisor told you, whether
that illustration has come to you in the policy bond or not, you can also check that here
. Here I have put my own photo. Actually the customer's photo
will be visible here. That means your photo will be visible. If your complete physical medical
test has been done here, then Tata AIA also provides you the reports.
You will see the complete physical medical reports here. Here you will also see your KYC documents
, which I have hidden here. Here you will also get complete details about the medical reports
. Your KYC documents will be mentioned here.
[Music] Here you will also
get to see the unit statement that how much of your money has gone into investment. In which funds it has gone.
In which fund it has gone. What is its current NAV? How many units have you received today
and what is your fund value at present? You
will be able to see that too here.
Here you have this receipt. You can also utilize it as a tax benefit
. This is the first premium receipt. You can avail the benefit under Section ATC of Income Tax
. If you file tax in the old regime, then you will see all these details
here. All the details that are most important will also be visible here
. In this way, this is the policy bond that comes to you. So do open it once
. Check. Is there any spelling error? Is there any error in the address?
Is there any error in the mobile number? Is there any error in the email ID?
Because all the communication that will happen in the future will happen on your mobile. It
happens on emails. There is no mismatch in the nominee details. Your education or income
has not been mentioned wrongly or there is some error. So did you
tell about all this existing insurance or not? You
have told the advisor about the health condition. You must also
check whether the advisor has mentioned it or not. Thank you. So you see, I have tried my best
to explain this policy bond to you and I have tried to explain
the claim process and all other details to you in great detail. If you
find this video of mine helpful, then definitely subscribe to my YouTube channel and
if you want to buy any company's policy after consulting and comparing it,
then you can also contact me on the number given below. Thank you so much. Jai
Hind.